Guide to the Roger Wilkins Papers 1968-2008
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Roger Wilkins papers
1928-2008
C0212
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
3.25 linear feet (9 boxes)
The papers document Wilkins' career while he was a professor at George Mason University. The documents include correspondence, publications, and speeches. There are also 14 videotape cassettes with lectures by other Robinson professors and media appearances by Wilkins.
Wilkins, Roger W., 1932-
The papers document Wilkins' career while he was a professor at George Mason University. The documents include correspondence, publications, and speeches. There are also 14 videotape cassettes with lectures by other Robinson professors and media appearances by Wilkins.
Series 1 contains the publications of Roger Wilkins and the various conferences, lecture series, and symposiums he attended and contributed to. The series includes articles he wrote organized by general subject, two of the books he published with various book reviews of the works, and the various flyers and papers of the conferences. The series is organized alphabetically by folder and then chronologically.
Series 2 contains Wilkins' general correspondence during his time as a Robinson professor. This series is organized chronologically by folder.
Series 3 contains the papers on the various organizations in which Wilkins was involved such as the African American Institute, the MacArthur Foundation, and the NAACP Legal Defense Fund. The series is organized alphabetically by folder and then chronologically.
Series 4 is made up of biographical material on Roger Wilkins. It includes articles he wrote describing himself as a father as well as other documents discussing his mother's and uncle's work for civil rights. There are also several transcribed interviews, one of which was conducted by one of his daughters. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder and then chronologically.
Series 5 contains various syllabi and notes from the classes Wilkins taught while at George Mason from 1990 through 2006. In addition there is information about the provost search in the spring of 1990. The series is organized alphabetically by folder and then chronologically.
Series 6 contains photographs, two cassette tapes of speeches, and 14 VHS tapes of lectures by Wilkins and other professors from 1995 through 2004. The series includes a funeral speech for George N. Lindsay given by Roger Wilkins as well as a letter from Lindsay's widow. This series is organized by medium and then chronologically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Arrangement
Organized into 6 series
Series 1: Publications, 1965-2008, (Boxes 1-5)
Series 2: General Correspondence, 1987-2006) (Box 5)
Series 3: Affiliations, 1995-2000, (Box 6)
Series 4: Biographical papers, 1928, 1963-2007 (Box 6)
Series 5: George Mason University, 1990-2006, (Boxes 7-8)
Series 6: Audio/Visual, 1994-2004, (Boxes 8-9; Oversize 1)
Related Material
Special Collections & Archives also holds the papers of other Robinson professors.
Biographical Information
Born in 1932 in Kansas City, Missouri, Roger Wilkins attended the University of Michigan and earned his Bachelor's degree in 1953 and his J.D. in 1956. He interned with Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP's Legal Defense Fund during his studies and his uncle, Roy Wilkins, served as the executive secretary of the NAACP from 1955 to 1977. In his early career, Roger Wilkins worked with the Ohio Welfare Department, the U.S. Agency for International Development, and as the assistant attorney general under President Lyndon B. Johnson. Following this, Wilkins pursued a successful career in journalism writing for The New York Times, The Washington Times, and editing The Washington Star. In 1972, as a member of The Washington Post's editorial staff, Wilkins along with Bob Woodward, Carl Bernstein, and Herbert Block earned the Pulitzer Prize for their coverage of the Watergate Scandal that led to President Nixon's resignation. A widely published author, Wilkins wrote A Man's Life, his autobiography, published first in 1982 and reprinted in 1991. In addition, Wilkins co-authored Quiet Riots: Race and Poverty in the United States with Fred Harris in 1988 and published Jefferson's Pillow: the Founding Fathers and the Dilemma of Black Patriotism in 2001. In 1986 he joined George Mason University as the Clarence Robinson Professor of History and American Culture and retired in 2007.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Roger Wilkins in 2012.
Index Terms
Persons:
Wilkins, Roger W., 1932-
Corporate Names:
George Mason University.
Geographical Names:
United States--Politics and government.
Subjects:
African Americans--Civil rights--History--20th century.
Contents List
- Series 1: Publications, 1965-2008; (4.5 boxes)
  This series includes articles and books written by Roger Wilkins, lectures, conferences, symposiums at which Roger Wilkins spoke, and the notes of the Pulitzer Prize committee.
  - Affirmative Action articles, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Man's Life and reviews, 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews, 1972-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles discussing Brown v Board, 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jefferson's Pillow and reviews, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lexus Nexus articles, January 1, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous articles, 1990-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles mentioning Roger Wilkins, 1987-2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous essays, 1980-2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Articles about Nelson Mandela and the Free South Africa Movement, 1974-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes and Speeches, 1968-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles discussing politics and elections, 1984-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pulitzer Prize, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Articles discussing race and racism, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles discussing race and racism, 1965-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Articles discussing race and racism, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles discussing race and racism, 1994-2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles with discussions between Shelby Steele and Roger Wilkins, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles discussing the Supreme Court, 1988-2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Conferences, Symposiums, and Lectures, 1983-1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Conferences, Symposiums, and Lectures, 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Conferences, Symposiums, and Lectures, 1996-2007 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, Symposiums, and Lectures: University of Michigan Lecture, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, Symposiums, and Lectures: DePauw Symposium, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Conferences, Symposiums, and Lectures, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series 2: General Correspondence, undated; 1987-2006; (1 box)
  This series contains Roger Wilkins correspondence from 1987 to 2006. It is organized chronologically.
  - Correspondence dealing with his work at NPR, February 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, 1987-1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence, 1998-2006 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Affiliations, 1995-2000; (0.5 box)
  This series includes organizations in which Roger Wilkins participated or headed from 1995 to 2000. It is organized alphabetically by organization then chronologically.
  - African American Institute, 1995-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Citizens' Commission on Civil Rights, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Legal Defense Fund, NAACP, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - MacArthur Foundation, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series 4: Biographical papers, undated; 1928; 1963-2007; (1 box)
  This series includes interviews with Roger Wilkins and biographical articles about him and his family.
  - Biographical articles, 1928; 1963-2007 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Interviews with Roger Wilkins, 1969-2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series 5: George Mason University, 1990-2006; (1.5 boxes)
  This series contains notes and syllabi of the classes Roger Wilkins taught while a Clarence Robinson professor of History and American Culture at George Mason University.
  - HNRS 130, 2003 and 2005 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Politics and the (Mass) Media, 1991-1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Politics and the (Mass) Media, 2000-2006 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Provost Search, January - April 1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Race, Law and Culture, 1991-1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Race, Law and Culture, 1996-1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - UNIV 190, 1996-2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series 6: Audio/Visual, undated; 1995-2004; (1.5 boxes)
  This series contains audio tapes and VHS tapes of lectures given by Roger Wilkins and other Robinson professors.
  - Photographs, undated; 2004 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - George N. Lindsay funeral speech, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - With Good Reason "Political Literacy: What Americans Should Know Before Voting", undated (Box 9, Cassette 1)
  - Harry Belafonte #1, undated (Box 9, Cassette 2)
  - Harry Belafonte #2, undated (Box 9, Cassette 3)
  - Bateson Lecture, undated (Box 9, Cassette 4)
  - Breakfast with Roger Wilkins, Dec 6, 1995 (Box 9, Cassette 5)
  - Close Up on CSPAN, Dec 7, 1995 (Box 9, Cassette 6)
  - Bateson Lecture #1, Feb 22, 1996 (Box 9, Cassette 7)
  - Bateson Lecture #2, Feb 22, 1996 (Box 9, Cassette 8)
  - Roger Wilkins Lecture #1, Mar 20, 1996 (Box 9, Cassette 9)
  - Roger Wilkins Lecture #2, Mar 20, 1996 (Box 9, Cassette 10)
  - Vassily Aksyonov #1, Apr 15, 1997 (Box 9, Cassette 11)
  - Vassily Aksyonov #2, Apr 15, 1997 (Box 9, Cassette 12)
  - Media Meet #9810 Civil Rights, January 19, 1998 (Box 9, Cassette 13)
  - A. Scott Bullitt Lecture in American History, January 14, 2003 (Box 9, Cassette 14)
  - For the Record #1105, May 6, 2004 (Box 9, Cassette 14)
  - Ceremonial Stage photo, May 18, 2005 (Oversize 1)
    The American Academy of Arts and Letters where Roger Wilkins was a keynote speaker. Wilkins is in the first row sixth from the right.